Guide to the Associated Students of Stanford University, Institute of International Relations, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Associated Students of Stanford University, Institute of International Relations, records
1948-1968
SC0046
Stanford University. Associated Students. Institute of International Relations
3.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
None.
Historical Note
The Institute of International Relations was formed in 1947 from a merger of the Stanford Overseas Information Service and other campus international groups. In addition to their regular program of speeches, publications, scholarships, and cultural activities, the IIR produced programs for high school students on international problems, sponsored the Stanford United Nations, and held an annual Foreign Policy Institute with speakers and seminars that was open to the general public. In 1961 the IIR established a relationship with Makerere University in Uganda, sending one Stanford student to East Africa each year. The Institute was the only student group to win the Freedoms Foundation medal. In the spring of 1968, the IIR and the International Club merged to form the International Association.
Scope and Content
Records include constitution and by-laws, correspondence, committee reports, budgets, speeches, clippings, and other materials, 1948-67, pertaining to the Foreign Policy Institutes, foreign scholarship program, high school conferences, Stanford United Nations, Books for Africa program, and other activities of the organization. Some of the correspondence pertains to visits by Dwight Eisenhower, Adlai Stevenson, Christian Herter, and other speakers. The collection also includes reports, publications, and other materials of the Institute for the Study of Contemporary Cultures, 1965-68.
Collection Contents
- Institute of International Relations, 1948-1967
  - Africa - Job placements, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Africa Desk, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African Forum, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Africa Secondary School Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Area Projects, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Asia Desk, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Atlantic Community Conference, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Batowski (Henryk A.) Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Berlin Affiliations, 1950-59 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Berlin Affiliations, 1960-62 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bastuoland - correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brandt, Karl - correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Budget, 1962-65 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - China Conference, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clay (Lucius) - correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conference Department, 1948, 1955-60 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1948-60 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Decision" Conference correspondence, 1964-65 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Denmark, proposed exchange with, 1951-54 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Eisenhower - correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - European correspondence, 1961-63 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Europe Week, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - External conferences, 1959-62 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Foreign Policy Institute's Chairmen's Reports, 1958-60 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 1, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 2, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 3, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 3, Press clippings, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 4, Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 4, Publicity, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 4, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 5, Speeches, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 5, Herter Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 5, Miscellaneous, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 7, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Foreign Policy Institute No. 7, Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Kahn (Herman) correspondence, Foreign Policy Institute, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Foreign Policy Institute, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Foreign Policy Institute, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Foreign Policy Institute, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Foreign Student Pre-registration, 1950-53 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Foreign Scholarship Program, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Foreign Scholarship Program, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Foreign Scholarship Program, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Foreign Scholarship Program Correspondence, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Foreign Scholarship Reports, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Foreign Students Advisor, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Foreign Students Trips and Tours, 1956-63 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Fund-Raising Activities, 1955-60 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Germany - correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Guttenberg (Baron Freiherr Zu) - correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Harriman (W. Averell) - correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Heiskell (Andrew) - correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - High School conferences, 1950-52 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - High School conferences, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - High School conferences reports, 1956-60 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - High School conferences, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - High School Desk, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - High School conference, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Host Program, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Hostel Series, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Internal Conferences, 1958-62 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - I-Center, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - I-Center, 1959-60 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - I-Center, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Student Division, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Keio University, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Korea, Proposed Exchange with, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Latin American Week, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Luce (John) - correspondence (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Moscow Affiliations, 1961-62 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Nagy (Ferenc) - correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - News clippings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1962-63 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Overseas Book Project, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Parker, Kenneth, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Policy Board Minutes, Jan-64 (Box 2, Folder 19a)
  - Price, Hickman, 1962-63 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - President's Office, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - IIR Programs, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Peace Corps, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rangarao (K. Shanthi) - correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ray, Phillip, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Report of the Committee on the Organization of Student International Affairs, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Reports, 1954-59 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Reports, 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Reports, Social Secretary, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Reports, Host Department, 1959-60 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Reports, Publicity, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Reports, Executive Secretary, 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Reports, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Reports, Social Division, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Reports, Quarterly, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Reports, Quarterly, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Reports, Quarterly, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Rostow (W. W.) - correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Scott, John C. - correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Stanford Overseas Information Service, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Speeches and Reports, 1958-64 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Stanford United Nations, Handbook, 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Stanford United Nations, Handbook, 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Stanford United Nations, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Stanford United Nations, Handbook, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - State Department - correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Stevenson - correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Szulc (Ted) - correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Warsaw Affiliations, 1960-62 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - World Affairs Council, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Zagoria (Donald S.) - correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Institute for the Study of Contemporary Cultures, 1965-68
  - Charter, staff list, and other miscellaneous material, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Political Science 99 Problems of International Relations: reports from Model United Nations, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publications (from the United Nations Desk), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Publications (lists, press releases, and bibliography on Mexican dance forms by Anya Peterson), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Research (photographs, clippings, article) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reference (member list, budget materials, minutes of Policy Board) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publicity (clippings and flyers) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Academic credit (correspondence, reports, form letters, memos for Political Science 99), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Activity credit (reports, form letters, memos, lists), 1965-67 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Researches in Latin American Society, edited by Anya Peterson and Ronald Royee, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Other
  - Association of International Relations Clubs, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Constitution, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Descriptive report of the first two years, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Policy Institute - Programs, 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Foreign Policy Institute - Proceedings of 5th Annual, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Handbook for foreign students (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History and Report, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - IIR History (1 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - IIR History (2 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - IIR History (3 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - IIR Informational Booklets (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The international student (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Introduction to Europe and Latin America, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Programs (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Travel Tips (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Vagabond, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 18)